Today's דף daf is what's going on here? Sorry. Excuse me. Something
went weird. Okay.
Today's דף daf is ס"ד Samech Dalet and we pick up from
the משנה Mishnah and let's get going in the middle of the
סוגיות sugyot that deal with פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu. We had the
first one which was the בית הלל בית שמאי Beis Hillel Beis
Shammai about boy and a girl or two boys and now we
are continuing with the next issue. Let's take a look. נשא אשה
ושהה עמה עשר שנים ולא ילדה. Nasa isha ve'shaha imah eser shanim
velo yalda.
If a man is with a woman for ten years and she
has not yet given birth. So of course one of the questions
is to him? Right, the question is exactly: why is it she
hasn't given birth? Is
the issue in her or in him?
So אינו רשאי לבטל.
eino rashai levatel.
He still cannot, because this picks up on the language of the
previous משנה, Mishnah, he can stop having kids once he has a
boy and a girl. So here it's saying that even if it's
ten years he can't say well that's
it let's just stop trying. Now of course again stop trying does
not mean using birth control, it means he can't let the situation
remain the way it is. He's got to do something about it.
What can he
do? He have to marry another woman, with or without divorcing his
first wife. So גירשה, geirshah, alright we'll talk about גירשה. geirshah. מותרת
להינשא לאחר. Muteret le'hinasay le'acher. So the implication is that he you
know again will either take another wife and divorce her or not
divorce her but either way take another wife. Now if he did
divorce her, מותרת להינשא לאחר, muteret le'hinasay le'acher,
she can marry another man, presumably even a man who has not
yet fulfilled פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu. We don't have to assume that
the inability to have kids
was rooted in her, and therefore she can get married to another
man and the man can hope that he'll fulfill the מצוה mitzvah
of פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu. ורשאי השני לשהות עמה עשר שנים. Ve'rashai
ha'sheni lish'hos imah eser shanim. And if they start not being able
to have kids, there's again another permission of ten years until he
have to do something about it. Now again the language of רשאי
rashai makes it sound like after ten years the man doesn't have
a choice. We will force the man again to either divorce her
or at least to marry another woman. So we'll see about that.
ואם הפילה מונה משעה
שהפילה. Ve'im hipila moneh mi'sha'ah she'hipila. If she miscarried, then you count
the ten years from the miscarriage because that miscarriage we don't see
that as an indication of infertility, some you know that maybe she's
able to get pregnant but not able to bring to term. We
actually see it as an indication of potential fertility and therefore you
count the ten years from that time. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, so
our Rabbis taught. נשא אשה ושהה עמה עשר שנים ולא ילדה יוציא
ויתן כתובה. Nasa isha ve'shaha imah eser shanim velo yalda yotzi ve'yitein
kesubah.
So here it's more explicit than the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah
was less explicit about what does it mean not to stop. Here
it says no he has to divorce her and give כתובה. kesubah.
Now why does he... well the גמרא Gemara will discuss marrying another
woman. This is assuming that the norm even if multiple wives are
allowed, the norm is certainly one wife. But the גמרא Gemara will
discuss that option, okay? But he's got to do something about it.
And ויתן כתובה, yitein kesubah, he has to give her כתובה. kesubah.
Now the כתובה kesubah payment, right this is sort of like the...
it's basically an idea of like it's a... it's not a no-fault
divorce type of a society. It's a fault divorce, whatever that's called.
And therefore the question is who's at fault determines whether or not
the woman gets her כתובה kesubah or not. If it was the
man who's at fault, he's divorcing her, well he doesn't have to
have done something bad, but let's just rephrase it this way: if
it wasn't the woman's fault that they're getting divorced then he have
to pay the כתובה. kesubah. So therefore the fact that he pays
the כתובה kesubah here shows that we're not allowed to assume, similar
to the משנה Mishnah where it said she can marry another man
who presumably hasn't fulfilled פרו ורבו, pru u'rvu, we're not allowed to
assume that it was her fault that they're not able to have
kids. Might have been his fault and therefore he have to pay
the כתובה. kesubah. Okay. שמא לא זכה להיבנות ממנה Shema lo zachah
le'hibanot mimena maybe it's him that he's not meriting to have kids
from her and it's not her. But he does have to divorce
her. Now ואף על פי שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר ve'af al
pi she'ein raya la'davar zecher la'davar because it says מקץ עשר שנים
לשבת אברם בארץ כנען mi'ketz eser shanim le'sheves Avram be'eretz Kena'an and
that's when Sarah gave him Hagar. So something was done about it
at that time. It's ten years already, you gotta do something. ללמדך
שאין ישיבת חוץ לארץ עולה מן המניין. Lelamedcha she'ein yeshivas chutz la'aretz
olah min haminyan. And therefore we can also infer from this is
that why only... I mean they hadn't had kids for a long
time, but it only counts ten years from the time they entered
into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So the time in חוץ לארץ chutz
la'aretz didn't count because maybe it was because of like רש"י Rashi
says the sin of living in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz that prevented
them from having kids. Okay. לפיכך חלה הוא או שחלתה היא.
Lefikach chalah hu o
she'chalsa hi.
Therefore
once we learn that you don't count towards the ten years things
that have other... can be attributed to other causes like living in
חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. So therefore if there's other reasons why, like
for example there was a period when he was sick or when
she was sick, או שניהם חבושים בבית האסורים o she'neihem chavushim be'veis
ha'asurim or they're both in prison. Interesting, both, why not either? But
okay. Anyway, אין עולים מן המניין. ein olim min haminyan. That does
not count towards the ten years. This can be
But that certainly allows
you to like consider other types of factors. What about factors like
stress? What about other things? Anyway, but certainly the חוץ לארץ Chutz
La'aretz would make a wide,
or, let me say it the other way, would extremely narrow the
application of this הלכה. halacha. Now the idea of יוציא ויתן כתובה,
yotzi ve'yiten ketubah, which is more explicit than the משנה, Mishnah, does
it mean that we literally compel divorce? Now one person is of
course well he can always marry another woman without divorcing her if
that was an acceptable norm. But let's even assume that's not the
case and he says I don't want to divorce her. Does he
have to divorce her or not? So if you take a look
at the first line of this תוספות, Tosafot, יוציא ויתן כתובה, yotzi
ve'yiten ketubah, תוספות Tosafot says, בסוף המדיר איכא פלוגתא דאמוראי כשנשא אשה
ושהה עשר שנים אם כופין אותו להוציא אם לאו. Besof Hamadir, itka
plugta de'amorai, keshenasa isha vesha'ah esser shanim, im kofin oto lehotzi im
lav. Okay,
so תוספות Tosafot says there's actually a debate whether we force a
divorce or not. And if you say you don't force, the language
of יוציא, yotzi, תוספות Tosafot says, doesn't literally mean you force him
to divorce, it's whatever it means that maybe that you want him
to get divorced or well then he even talks about even verbal
compelling and he says maybe you don't do that either. Okay, but
anyway, but תוספות Tosafot basically says that the language of יוציא yotzi
does not necessarily mean that you force, it means like should maybe.
But that becomes a very interesting question right because nowadays there's a
famous רמ"א Rema in שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch that basically says, I
mean there's a whole סוגיא sugya in כתובות Ketubot about reasons, things
you would compel divorce for, and this is not to be confused
necessarily with the עגונה agunah issues. This is a case where other
types of issues, for example a man's wife, they both want to
stay married and there's a question in the גמרא Gemara do you
still compel divorce? Like the woman doesn't cover her hair. So there's
a question in the גמרא Gemara do you compel divorce? Okay. So
the רמ"א Rema basically says that nowadays we don't force people to
get divorced, you know, I mean he's not talking about like, it
gets into a question about let's say a כהן Kohen and a
גרושה gerushah etc., at times when there was more,
when the Jewish communities had more
autonomous power and ability to actually to compel certain things. But certainly
things that are not that degree of a violation, we don't compel
divorce. And in this issue itself the גמרא Gemara itself questions whether
we would compel a divorce at all. So even though it has
the language of יוציא, yotzi, תוספות Tosafot immediately points out that should
not be interpreted to mean that we that we compel it.
Okay, but is there another option?
Well, clearly יוציא yotzi means should, but should doesn't mean that we
force.
Okay.
So now let's take a look.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, yeah.
Okay, so now
the
גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמרי ליה לרב נחמן ולילף מיצחק, Amreleh leRav Nachman, ve'leilaf
mi'Yitzchak, why not learn it from יצחק? Yitzchak? דכתיב ויהי יצחק בן
ארבעים שנה בקחתו את רבקה. Dichsiv Vayehi Yitzchak ben arbaim shana bekachto
et Rivka. He was forty years. ודכתיב ויצחק בן ששים
שנה בלדת אתם. ve'Dichsiv ve'Yitzchak ben shishim shana be'ledet otam. Not till
sixty
till he had kids,
and he only started praying presumably right before she got pregnant. So
it seems like they waited twenty years before he felt that he
had to do something about it. תוספות Tosafot says, well according to
the מדרש Midrash that רבקה Rivka was only three when he got
married, there's no question because he had to wait till she was
anyway about twelve till she could have kids, so it works out
perfectly. But he says okay, but this גמרא Gemara isn't assuming that
מדרש. Midrash. אמרי ליה, Amrelei, so he said back, יצחק עקר היה.
Yitzchak akar hayah. No, יצחק Yitzchak himself was unable to have kids
and therefore it wasn't, there wasn't anything to... it wasn't about like
getting another wife or something of that nature because it was his
problem. So it was actually both of their problems but okay, but
it was his problem too. So the גמרא Gemara said, so if
you're an עקר akar then you don't then you're allowed to keep
your wife with you and she won't have kids?
Yeah, well that's going to get, that's a good question, that's going
to get to the issue about whether women are מצווה על פרו
ורבו metzuva on pru u'rvu or even if they're not מצווה על
פרו ורבו metzuva on pru u'rvu they have a right to get
divorced if they want to get divorced and have kids. We're going
to get to that. Okay. Of course it's still funny because even
if he was an עקר akar then he still waited twenty years
before praying for himself, for both of them, for doing anything. But
anyway, what did he wait for? He didn't take another wife, he
just waited to pray. So I don't know. Anyway, אי הכי I
hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's the issue that you can't
learn it from there because the problem was with
him, אברהם נמי עקר היה. Avraham nami akar hayah. So אברהם Avraham
also was sterile. How do we know this? We'll see in a
little bit in a minute in a דרשה drasha in the גמרא.
Gemara. So therefore maybe again maybe it doesn't prove anything because even
though even though you know that even though he did wait ten
years, it's not, it doesn't make, you can't learn from it because...
as it was, he can't, in theory, he shouldn't have been able
to do anything about it. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, ההוא
hahu מיבעי ליה mibaye lei לחזקיה בר אבא. leChizkiyah bar Abba. No,
you know what, the reason it says the 20 years from יצחק,
Yitzchak, you're right, forget about the fact that they were עקור akur
or whatever, bracket all that, but the reason you can't learn out
from יצחק Yitzchak is because you need it to tell me... the
reason it mentions he was 40 when he got married and 60
when he had kids was not to learn out a halachic principle.
It was to learn out the teaching of חזקיה בר אבא, Chizkiyah
bar Abba, דאמר חזקיה בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, d'amar Chizkiyah bar
Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, למה נמנו שנותיו של ישמעאל כדי ליחס בהן
שנותיו של יעקב? Lama nimnu shnotav shel Yishmael kedei leyaches bahen shnotav
shel Yaakov? Why did it tell you how old ישמעאל Yishmael was
in order that you should be able to figure out how old
יעקב Yaakov was when יעקב Yaakov ran away from the house and
then how old he was when he came back, and a whole
big thing
which is worked out in another גמרא. Gemara. So the basic point
is, though, that the reason it tells you, no, because you have
to know how old יעקב... Yaakov... like when was יעקב Yaakov born
relative to how old יצחק Yitzchak was born... I'm not going to
go through the whole discussion, okay, רש''י Rashi doesn't even go through
the discussion. Anyway, so,
the point is, it tells you the years in order to learn
out other aspects of the history, of the sort of, of the
chronology there, but not to tell you something about the significance of
him having waited 20 years. So yeah, okay, it mentions it in
passing, that's for a different purpose of sort of figuring out the
chronology, but by
אברהם, Avraham, there was no other person, why would it, reason why
it would have indicated he waited 10 years until this event was
הגר Hagar other than to tell you this halachic principle that after
10 years you gotta do something about it. Yes, Charlie.
Why don't they bring up the question of why יצחק Yitzchak and
יעקב Yaakov wait so long before getting married, because פרו ורבו peru
urevu should be...
All right,
so that idea that you have to get married right away in
order to do פרו ורבו peru urevu is nowhere in the גמרא.
Gemara. That's, the גמרא Gemara speaks about getting married young so a
person is not... man isn't preoccupied by sexual thoughts, does not talk
about it in terms of פרו ורבו. peru urevu. It's the רמב''ם
Rambam that tries to sort of introduce that idea within פרו ורבו,
peru urevu, but the simple sense of the גמרא Gemara is you
start worrying about פרו ורבו peru urevu once you get married. You
know, it's not like you have to get married in order to
take care of פרו ורבו. peru urevu. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
Okay. אמר רבי יצחק יצחק אבינו עקור היה. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak Yitzchak
Avinu akur haya. Now we're going to say why we're assuming that
both יצחק Yitzchak and אברהם Avraham were sterile. יצחק Yitzchak was sterile,
שנאמר, shene'emar, ויעתר יצחק לה' לנוכח אשתו. Vaye'etar Yitzchak l'Hashem lenochach ishto.
יצחק Yitzchak prayed to Hashem for the sake of his wife. על
אשתו לא נאמר, Al ishto lo ne'emar, for his wife it didn't
say, אלא לנוכח, ella lenochach, what does that mean? מלמד ששניהם עקורים
היו. Melamed sheshneihem akurim hayu. Okay,
so all right, so it's a good point. So לנוכח lenochach somehow
means the sense of
parallel, so the same way she was an עקרה, akarah, he was
an עקור akur as well. אי הכי I hachi says the גמרא,
Gemara, if that's true, ויעתר לו, vaye'etar lo, God responded to him,
ויעתר להם מיבעי ליה, vaye'etar lahem mibaye lei, he responded to them.
Now that's a strange question because either way what does it mean...
why is it now more of a question because he is the
one that's also sterile? It says when he was praying for her,
it says ויעתר לו ה', vaye'etar lo Hashem, God responded to him
because even though it was for her, he was the one praying.
So now just because he's also sterile, it should say ויעתר להם,
vaye'etar lahem, right?
So the מהרש''א Maharsha says very beautifully, he says no, because what
this... why... the idea here is that יצחק Yitzchak is praying for
רבקה, Rivka, right? He's praying לנוכח אשתו, lenochach ishto, and that fits
into a גמרא Gemara idea about praying on behalf of somebody else.
Right, you know the גמרא Gemara כל המתפלל על חברו הוא נענה
תחילה, kol hamitpallel al chavero hu ne'eneh techilah, if you pray for
somebody else then you're answered first. But the idea about not praying...
you know, that it's more effective for you to pray for somebody
else than for somebody to pray for themselves. So he says, so
here יצחק Yitzchak is praying for רבקה, Rivka, and if רבקה Rivka's
the only one
that's unable to have kids, he's praying for רבקה Rivka and he's
answered. But if יצחק Yitzchak is unable to have kids, then who's
praying for יצחק? Yitzchak? So who's praying for
יצחק? Yitzchak? רבקה! Rivka! So if יצחק Yitzchak is unable to have
kids, then רבקה Rivka obviously is also praying for יצחק. Yitzchak. So
then it should be ויעתר להם, vaye'etar lahem, so God should be
responding to both of them. Okay, so it's a very nice way
the מהרש''א Maharsha reads this גמרא. Gemara. We're assuming that the person
who has...
the other person is praying for the one who has the problem.
So ויעתר יצחק לה' לנוכח אשתו, Vaye'etar Yitzchak l'Hashem lenochach ishto, על
אשתו, Al ishto, anyway, ויעתר להם מיבעי ליה, vaye'etar lahem mibaye lei,
because if he's got the problem then she's praying for him
too. לפי, Lefi, what about... we're assuming the way... לפי שאינו דומה
תפלת צדיק בן צדיק לתפלת צדיק בן רשע. Lefi she'eino domeh tfilat
tzaddik ben tzaddik litfilat tzaddik ben rasha. You're right, God they both
did pray, but it emphasized responding to him because it's not similar
the prayer of a צדיק tzaddik the son of a צדיק tzaddik
to the prayer of a צדיק tzaddik the son of or the
child of a רשע. rasha. So yes, they were both praying, but
ultimately it was his prayers that were answered. Some hierarchy there. Yeah,
what can I tell you. Anyway, by the way, somebody once pointed
out to me many years ago that this גמרא Gemara is actually
quite strange because normally the idiom אינו דומה eino domeh X ל-Y
is which one is more important?
When you say אינו דומה...
Normally it's the second one which is more important, right?
It's that אינה דומה einah domeh so-and-so to this. This, you know,
so it's funny because it's אינה דומה תפילת צדיק בן צדיק לתפילת
צדיק בן רשע. einah domeh tefilat tzadik ben tzadik l'tefilat tzadik ben
rasha. The normal structure of that idiom is that the one mentioned
second is the one that's more important, but it's clearly not the
intention of this גמרא. Gemara.
So I don't know what you do with that.
The second one is
the one that's more powerful for somebody that's a...
I understand. It's like במקום שבעלי תשובה עומדים אין צדיקים גמורים יכולים
לעמוד. b'makom she'ba'alei teshuvah omdim ein tzadikim gemurim yecholim la'amod. Right. And
that's the structure of the normal structure of that idiom. But I
don't know how it fits in here. You know, it'd
be interesting if you could find a way to read it that
that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying, but somehow it still has
to end with it being ויעתר לו ה׳, vaye'atar lo Hashem, that
God responds, so I don't know how that fits in. Okay, אמר
רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, מפני מה היו אבותינו עקורים? mipnei mah
hayu avoteinu akurim? Why were our forefathers, we would say foremothers? I
mean obviously it's the דרש, drash, it's also אברהם ויצחק, Avraham v'Yitzchak,
but clearly in the פסוקים... psukim... yeah, we're going to get to
אברהם Avraham later. But anyway, but clearly in the פסוקים psukim it's
the mothers that are... that have problems with having kids. מפני שהקדוש
ברוך הוא מתאווה לתפילתן של צדיקים. mipnei she'Hakadosh Baruch Hu mit'aveh l'tefilatan
shel tzadikim. Because God desires the prayers of the righteous. Right? I
mean there's in general a question, right? Why is it that all
of the, you know, like just came up in last week's פרשה,
parsha, right? You know, every time that the אבות avot you know,
have this challenge
and the אמהות imahot with kids, you see how their counterparts have
a high degree of fertility, right? אברהם Avraham returns from the עקדה
akeidah and what does he find out? That נחור Nachor had twelve
kids like poof, like just like that, no problem, right? And then
you have, you know, you have the whole story with like יצחק
Yitzchak and the praying and finally יעקב Yaakov and עשו Esav or
whatever. ישמעאל, Yishmael, twelve kids, right? And then you have with יעקב,
Yaakov, right, and the whole travail he has, and then you have
עשו Esav and he's got all these מלכים, melachim, all these kids
and all these nations and so on. So anyway, so obviously the
whole story is that the path of true, you know, of like
true blessing, not of easy blessing, comes with a lot of travail.
So the גמרא Gemara here is framing it as God
wanted, was desirous for their prayers. But obviously it's something that requires
more elaboration because that's obviously a major part of the whole message
there, that here is the nation that is blessed and they're the
ones that are having the greatest sort of challenge in the world,
but on the other hand they're also having the greatest closeness to
God in the process.
Yeah, and you know what else is so striking, it's so formulaic,
right? צדיק בן צדיק tzadik ben tzadik to תפילת צדיק בן רשע.
tefilat tzadik ben rasha. But really it's talking about צדיק בת רשע,
tzadik bat rasha, right? But it's like they have this formula. Right,
they never have women in mind, they're rhetorically just put as
'ben' and they never
change the rhetoric.
Totally, totally. Okay, אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, למה נמשלה תפילתן
של צדיקים כעתר? lamah nimshelah tefilatan shel tzadikim k'atar?
Why is the prayers of the righteous like a pitchfork? Because
it says ויעתר יצחק לה׳. vaye'atar Yitzchak l'Hashem. Yitzchak importuned God. But
the word עתר atar is like a pitchfork. מה עתר זה מהפך
את התבואה ממקום למקום, mah atar zeh mehapech et hatvuah mimakom l'makom,
the same way a pitchfork you use to turn over the grain,
the wheat, from one place to another, כך תפילתן של צדיקים מהפכת
מדותיו של הקדוש ברוך הוא ממדת רוגז למדת רחמנות. kach tefilatan shel
tzadikim mehapechet midotav shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu mimiddat rogez l'middat rachmanut. So
similarly the prayers of the צדיקים tzadikim flip God's
attributes of anger to attributes of compassion. And now to end this
idea that אברהם Avraham had the problem as well, אמר רבי אמי,
Amar Rabbi Ami, אברהם ושרה טומטומים היו. Avraham v'Sarah tumtumim hayu. They
were טומטומים. tumtumim. They were originally ones that did not have their
gender was not initially or their sex was not initially identifiable. Their
genitalia. And it's assumed that if you're a טומטום tumtum you're going
once that problem is addressed, you're going to remain
infertile or have a challenge with fertility.
אינו יוליד ואינה יולדת?
eino
yolid v'einah yoledet?
Well okay, but that... no, we're talking about primary genitalia.
Anyway, this is only initially. But we're going to assume that even
after their condition is fixed, you're still going to remain infertile or
have a challenge with fertility.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, הביטו אל צור חצבתם ואל מקבת בור נקרתם. habitu el
tzur chutzavtem v'el makevet bor nukartem. Look at the rock from which
you were hewn and from the
hole
in which you were chiseled out of, the well.
וכתיב, U'chtiv, הביטו אל אברהם אביכם ואל שרה תחוללכם. habitu el Avraham
avichem v'el Sarah techolelchem. Look at אברהם Avraham your father and שרה
Sarah the one who gave birth to you. So you have the
idea
of they required... they weren't yet finally formed initially, right? They had
to be chiseled out. So his actual genitalia had not yet... it
can't... it's come out, right? It was somehow covered by some type
of a membrane. And by שרה Sarah as well. So there was
a still an unformed nature of them. I'm sure you could do...
Bizarre. It's, yes, it is very bizarre. And I'm sure you could
do very interesting things with this מדרש. midrash. I don't have anything
to say about it at this time. אמר נחמן. Amar Nachman. Okay,
anyway, so it's quite fascinating it wasn't just Sarah... and Rivka, but
it was אברהם Avraham and יצחק Yitzchak that were also challenged with
fertility, but nevertheless, because the פסוק Pasuk goes out of its way
to mention ten years by אברם, Avram, we use that as some
type of a basis for this idea. אמר רבא בר אבוה:
Amar
Rava
bar Avuha: שרה אמנו איילונית היתה.
Sarah Imeinu Ayalonit hayata.
Now that we’re talking about that she was a טומטום, tumtum, if
that's not enough, she was also an איילונית. ayalonit. An איילונית ayalonit
as we know is not a woman that's just an עקרה, akara,
infertile, but actually something very physically different with her body that's indicative
of that
state. And here he's going to spell one of that, one aspect
of that out. שנאמר: shenemar: ותהי שרי עקרה אין לה ולד. Vatehi
Sarai akara ein lah valad. שרי Sarai was an infertile, she had
no child. So why does it have to say that? If she's
infertile she obviously had no child. To tell you: אפילו בית ולד
אין לה, afilu beit valad ein lah, she did not even have
a uterus. So that's makes her more of an איילונית ayalonit as
opposed to just an עקרה. akara.
And also then of course shows part of the reason the גמרא
Gemara might be doing this is to show the degree of the
נס nes that then they had kids even though both of them
had all of these physical challenges and challenges with fertility. אמר רב
יהודה בריה דרב שמואל בר שילת משמיה דרב: Amar Rav Yehuda brei
deRav Shmuel bar Shilas mishmei deRav: לא שנו אלא בדורות הראשונים, lo
shanu ela bedorot harishonim, ששנותיהם מרובות. sheshnoteihem merubot. Back then, this ten-year
wait is only in the earlier
generations that they lived 180 years or however long they lived. This
shows you what happens when you link it to אברהם. Avraham. Okay,
on the one hand it's a nice link, but on the other
hand, oh well, that was by אברהם. Avraham. That was when they
lived so long. אבל בדורות אחרונים aval bedorot acharonim nowadays, ששנותיהם מועטות,
sheshnoteihem muatot, when we live much less, right, שתי שנים ומחצה, shtei
shanim umechtza, then you have to do something about it after only
two and a half years. That's a pretty radical change in the
הלכה. Halacha. Okay, כנגד שלשה עיבורים keneged shelosha iburim to give you
time for like three cycles. Okay, three times nine months is 27
months, so you assume one month in between to get pregnant again,
so three times ten is 30 months which is two and a
half years. Okay, so you're trying over what would have been three
cycles. Of course it's funny because actually it's like over 30 months,
that's 30 opportunities to get pregnant, but nevertheless, you're giving for whatever
reason this is like seen as like a חזקה, chazaka, three cycles.
It's again, I don't really understand why you measure, you know, the
how do you measure the absence of pregnancy based on how long
it would have been had you been pregnant? But anyway, three cycles
and then obviously something is wrong and then you gotta get divorced.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying the הלכה Halacha is the same,
that is to say after some period of time you need to
do something. What's sociologically determined is the amount of.
I wouldn't say sociologically. This is saying you have fewer years to
live, so you and you have fewer years of fertility and you
gotta work on it faster.
In other words contextual, the number of years is contextual.
רבא אמר רב נחמן: Rava amar Rav Nachman:
שלש שנים. shalosh shanim. No, three full years. כנגד שלש פקידות, keneged
shalosh pekidot, three times that God visits, you know, opportunities to be
visited and remembered by God. דאמר מר: de’amar mar: בראש השנה נפקדו
שרה רחל וחנה. berosh Hashanah nifkedu Sarah Rachel veChannah. So you want
to have three ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanahs. So I don't know why
we don't say three ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanahs, but okay, we give
you, you know, maybe God remembers you on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
and then something happens after the ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So it's
a way of sort of making it a similar number for everyone.
אמר רבא: Amar Rava: לית להו להני כללי. leis lehu lehani klalei.
No, forget those rules that you just said that two and a
half years, three years. מכדי, michdi, let's take a look. מתניתין מאן
תקין? matnitin man takin? רבי. Rabbi. Who wrote our
משנה? Mishnah? רבי. Rabbi. והא בימי דבי ve’ha bi’ymei d'bei he was
living fewer years. דכתיב: dechtiv: ימי שנותינו בהם שבעים שנה ואם בגבורות,
yemei shnoteinu bahem shiv’im shanah ve’im bigvurot, whatever, 70 years. Okay. So
therefore forget all that very nice that they want to revise it,
but no, sorry, our משנה Mishnah stands ten years, our משנה Mishnah
is being פסק paskin'd for אברהם אבינו, Avraham Avinu, our משנה Mishnah
is being פסק paskin'd for normal people. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara
says by the way you do have to understand that if the
man is remarried, I mean, you know, if he remarries as was,
you know, happens today and was definitely common then as then even
more common then as is, you know, an older man gets remarried,
he'll, you know, marry a much younger woman. So even if he's
getting on in years, his fertility, you know, his fertility is not
the one off that's going to be challenged by the increase in,
you know, in age, so saying wait ten years isn't like, oh
my god then he'll never have kids. No, I mean, you know,
he might if he gets remarried to a much younger woman. And
it actually gives them a lot of time, you know, much more
time to hopefully that they will have kids.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: והאי שמא לא
זכו לבנות ממנה ודילמא מדידיה לא זכיה. ve'hai shema lo zachu lebanot
mimena vedi'alma midai lo zachya.
So how do we know, why we say, well maybe the problem
was with him? And therefore that explains why he has to give
the כתובה. ketuvah. Yeah, maybe it's with him, but maybe it's with
her. Why do we sort of say like המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה,
hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah, right? Certainly some because at least one of
you not having kids. So if she wants to collect her כתובה,
ketuvah, let her prove that it's his problem. Why are we assuming,
which raises an interesting question, right, about what do you do in
a case of a ספק safek when you don't know whose problem
it is? Is she fundamentally entitled to get the כתובה ketuvah or
not? Who has to prove fault here? Or who has to prove,
you know, what's the default assumption? But the גמרא Gemara at least
wants to ask why aren't we at least willing to consider the
likelihood that it's her problem?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, כיוון דלא מיפקדא א פרו ורבו
לא מיענשא. Kivan d'lo amifkada a p'ru u'rvu lo m'ancha. So assuming
like we're going to say later, which is a debate later of
תנאים, Tannaim, whether a woman is commanded in פרו ורבו, p'ru u'rvu,
but assuming that she's not commanded in פרו ורבו, p'ru u'rvu, so
we look at the inability to have kids as a punishment and
we figure out who's being punished. Well, who's being punished is the
person that's not being able to fulfill their obligation, so it must
be the man is being punished, it must be that therefore it's
coming as a result of him. Which is again very hard to
hear because for women who actually, I mean it's one thing which
we'll get to about what does it mean for women who are
having the kids and to say they're not commanded
on פרו ורבו, p'ru u'rvu, but the women are the ones that
actually being pregnant and the child is gestating in their body and
they're the ones giving birth to the kids and to say that
the inability to have kids is not something that she feels like
she's suffering as a result because it wasn't her מצוה mitzvah so
she's not suffering as a result, he's the one that's suffering. What?
No, maybe it's not meaning like we're saying that on top of
all the troubles we're not going to say now it's your fault,
right? So maybe a little bit more...
Oh, so you're saying we're not going... that's interesting. So you're saying,
okay that's a nice twist. You want to say we're not saying
objectively he's being punished and she's not, we're saying like הלכתית halachically
we're going to identify it as his fault and not... okay, I'm
not sure the גמרא Gemara intended that, but that's a nice read
of the גמרא. Gemara.
In addition to that, she's therefore, she's then, if they do get
divorced, she collects the כתובה. ketubah.
I understand, I understand this is all in her benefit. I'm just
saying to just... but Michael, but what you and Michael are saying
is essentially the same, like we're going to choose to frame this
as his fault. Okay, again I'm not sure that's what the גמרא
Gemara meant, but I'll accept that. So the גמרא Gemara says והא
איני והא אמרו ליה רבנן לרבי אבא בר זבדא נסיב איתתא ואוליד
בני. Veha eini veha amru leh rabanan l'rabbi abba bar zavda nasiv
iteta v'olid b'ni. The rabbis said to Rabbi Abba bar Zavda, I
don't understand, you've had one kid but now your wife let's say
is past, why don't you remarry and try to have another kid?
And we've saw this before, ואמר להו זכאי הוה לי מקמייתא, V'amar
lehu zakai havah li mikamaita, and he said back to them, had
I merited it, I would have had kids with my first wife,
since I didn't have kids with my first wife, I'm not going
to have with my second wife. Okay, so what does that prove?
So why... ah, so meaning, yes, he's sort of saying that it's
his fault, but he's saying like absolutely you won't have kids. Our
whole idea is that maybe you weren't זוכה zocher to have kids
with the first woman, but you'll be זוכה zocher to have kids
with another woman, meaning not like that's again sort of started the
assumption... let's just take a moment and appreciate the irony of what
the גמרא Gemara is saying. It's saying marry another woman. By saying
marry another woman, basically we're saying that with another woman might be
fertile and this woman is not. And at the same time we're
saying, but give the first wife the כתובה, ketubah, which means that
it's not her problem, it's your problem. So how do you get
both? If she gets a כתובה ketubah and it's not her problem,
why should you have the obligation to marry another woman? Clearly it's
your problem. So that's why it's framed as לא זכה להיבנות ממנה.
Lo zachah l'hibanot mimenah. Somehow it's not working with you and her
together, but it might work with you and another woman. But that's
not going so far to say that she's the cause of it.
So it's a very
interesting line that it's walking on all along, which is very fascinating,
right? It basically protects the wife's interests, tells her she can get
remarried, another man can marry her doesn't have to worry that she
won't have kids, she's entitled to her כתובה, ketubah, and at the
other hand sort of tells the man, but you still have to
keep on trying to have kids. So it works in that little
middle space. It's not exactly her problem, but it's not exactly your
problem in an absolute way. Try with another woman. So that's a
fascinating middle space. So the גמרא Gemara is saying is that true?
Look, they said to this Rabbi get remarried and he said no,
I'm not going to have kids. If I didn't have kids with
the first one, I won't have kids with the second one.
Doesn't that show the issue is him and how does merit factor
in one way or another?
Well, that's why like the גמרא Gemara about מיענשא, m'ancha, the גמרא
Gemara sort of sees that it's like about some intersection between the
physical reality, medical
reality, and God's intervention. So I don't know, I mean the idea
of God and praying to God, I mean there's other פסוקים psukim
how God remembering and causing a pregnancy. So there's obviously seen to
be some intersection between that. Right, I mean, you could try to
maybe medically say it, that if he's got let's say, if they
both have some problems, then together they won't have kids, but maybe
if each one of them is married to somebody who has no
fertility problems, they'll both have kids, right? You could have said it
medically too.
Yeah, and there's a lot, a lot that we don't understand scientifically
about fertility even though we think we know a lot about it.
But for an individual case it's very difficult
to determine. I know a rabbinic couple in Israel spent years trying
to conceive a child, they finally had twins, and then very quickly
after the twins were born they had two more kids without any
intervention at all. Right. And that's...
Yeah, and look, you hear these stories about like also things like
almost like the שרה Sarah and הגר Hagar case, like a family
doesn't have kids, they adopt a kid and then right afterwards they
have their own kid, things like that. Yeah, that happens, I hear
those types of stories a lot. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this... Okay, so is it really true that you'll be זוכה
zocheh with another woman? But he said, look, if I didn't have
kids with the first one, I won't have kids with the next
one. So the גמרא Gemara says התם דחובה קא מדחי להו דרבנן.
Hasam de-chovah ka medachi lehu de-rabbanan. No, there he was just pushing
the rabbis off. You know, as we saw this before. רב אבא
בר זבדי אקם מפרקיה דרב הונא Rav Abba bar Zavdi akam mi-pirkeih
de-Rav Huna because רב אבא בר זבדי Rav Abba bar Zavdi actually
became sterile from the going to the שיעור shiur of רב הונא
Rav Huna and he kept on talking and he couldn't we saw
that before couldn't excuse himself to go to the bathroom and that
led him becoming sterile. So
therefore it was totally his fault and it was totally as a
result of him and there was no issue that it would work
out with another woman. רב גידל אקם מפרקיה
דרב הונא. Rav Giddel akam mi-pirkeih de-Rav Huna. Now רב גידל Rav
Giddel also did this. Oh my God, somebody should have said something
to רב הונא. Rav Huna. רב חלבו אקם מפרקיה דרב הונא. Rav
Chelbo akam mi-pirkeih de-Rav Huna. רב ששת אקם מפרקיה דרב הונא. Rav
Sheshet akam mi-pirkeih de-Rav Huna. רב אחא בר יעקב, Rav Acha bar
Yaakov, okay fine. רב אחא בר יעקב
אחדתיה סוכסכינא Rav Acha bar Yaakov achadteih sucsachina so he had this
problem, this thing called I don't know סוכסכינא sucsachina which is some
type of a urinary infection or and he's not able to urinate
or some type of a thing of that nature maybe it's causing
sterility. תלווה בארזא דבי רב Talvuh be-arza de-bei Rav so they suspended
him I don't know upside down, right side up, they suspended him
from the cedar tree in the in the house of רב Rav
or whatever the the as the property of רב Rav ונפיק מיניה
כוחשא ירקא ve-nafik mineih kuchsha yarka and
it emitted from him like a green like like you know a
green palm leaf so a stream of urine or something like that.
So anyway and that presumably healed his problems. אמר רב אחא בר
יעקב Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov שיתין סבי הוינא shitin sabei havina
we were sixty elders וכולהו אקמו מפרקיה דרב הונא ve-kuleihu akmu mi-pirkeih
de-Rav Huna and all of us got you know became sterile as
a result of sitting in רב הונא's Rav Huna שיעור shiur לבר
מינאי le-var minai except for me. Just got to be a joke
right they were just messing around.
I don't know. דקיימי בנפשאי de-kaymi be-nafshai I fulfilled in myself החכמה
תחיה בעליה. hachochmah techayeh ve-aleha. I started looking around and seeing what
was happening so I excused myself to go to the bathroom maybe
I went to the bathroom ahead of time I don't know anyway
I was the only one. All right moving on. גירשא מותרת. Geirsha
mutereset. So now we have this interesting again middle category that it's
not it's not her fault she gets divorced but gets her כתובה
kesubah she marries somebody else and but he is goes ahead and
is still told to try again. Now now we get to the
point that if again if she is divorced she can marry somebody
else because again we don't yet have evidence that it's her fault.
So the גמרא Gemara says the following. Now we get into a
very classic גמרא Gemara relating to issues of חזקה. chazakah. Let's take
a look. שני אין Sheni in she can marry the second guy.
שלישי לא Shelishi lo she can't marry a third guy. Okay let's
say it happened twice in a row. Okay two guys ten years
with each of them no kids. Should a third man who hasn't
had kids yet be allowed to marry her? And the גמרא's Gemara
saying since the משנה Mishnah didn't say so it only said she
can marry a second guy presumably she can't marry a third guy.
At that stage we would assume that she is infertile.
All right I don't know it's a good point let's say she
started at twelve. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says מתניתין מני רבי
היא. Masnitin mani Rabbi hi. Our משנה Mishnah is רבי. Rabbi. דתניא
דתנן בברייתא. de-tanya de-tnan be-vrayta. Now we're going to get to issues
about this is normally framed as after how many times do you
establish a חזקה chazakah two or three times. But as you will
see it's not exactly the issue of a חזקה chazakah it's more
about a question about when do you have to be start
concerned you know. חזקה Chazakah means I'm sort of giving you away
the secret at the end but okay חזקה chazakah means that something
is habitual. You know if it's happened three times you know it's
going to happen like regularly. But there's a middle ground between saying
it's you know it was a freak occurrence and saying that it
happens every single time. And it's saying like there's enough that you
have to here be concerned that it's going to happen and do
something about it. So think let's think about that and let's look
at this debate. דתניא De-tanya we taught in a ברייתא. beraita. מלה
הראשונה ומת. Malah ha-rishonah va-mes.
So you did a ברית מילה bris milah on the first kid
of a family and he died. שני ומת Sheni va-mes and the
second one and he died as a result. שלישי
לא תמול Shelishi lo simol do not give a ברית מילה bris
milah to the third one. דברי רבי. Divrei Rabbi. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אמר Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omar שלישי תמול shelishi simol no
you give a ברית מילה bris milah to the third one and
if he dies then רביעי לא תמול revi'i lo simol don't the
fourth. Now as you can of course see here is you might
say look buddy three times you might need three times for a
חזקה chazakah but after one time I'm not doing any ברית מילה
bris milah to these kids right let alone two times. So that's
why it's not really a question about it's not really fair to
frame this as a question of how many times make a חזקה.
chazakah. But here we see that after two times you start worrying
according to רבי Rabbi and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel you need three. והתניא איפכא Ve-hatanya ipecha but we've got a
ברייתא beraita that reversed which was רבי Rabbi and which was רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So the גמרא Gemara says
הי מינייהו אחריתא Hei mineihu achrita which is the last one? Which
is the one that establishes really who which is רבי's Rabbi position
and which is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל's? Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel תא
שמע. Ta shema. דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן De-amar
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan it's a story with רבי
חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba in the name of רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. מעשה בארבע אחיות בציפורי Ma'aseh be-arba achayot be-Tzipori a
story of four sisters in ציפורי Tzipori שמה הראשונה ומת she-malah ha-rishonah
va-mes the first one gave a ברית מילה bris milah to her
son and he died ושניה ומת שלישית ומת ve-shniya va-mes shelishit va-mes
so all these sisters had baby boys and every one of them
had a child and went you know gave a ברית מילה bris
milah and the boy died. רביעית באת לפני רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Revi'it ba'at lifnei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel the fourth she came before
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. אמר לה, Amar lah, he said to her,
אל תמולי, al tamoli, don't give ברית מילה. Bris Milah. So you
see רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel waited for three
before saying it, so he's the one that says three. So the
גמרא Gemara says well we'll talk about that in a minute. ודילמא
אי אסקיה שלישית נמי הוה אמר לה. Ve-dilma ee askya shlishis nami
hava amar lah. So the גמרא Gemara says that doesn't prove anything
because he was only asked after three times. Maybe if he was
asked by the third sister, he would have said don't do it
even after don't do it because of the other two kids, because
two kids had already happened to. So is the fact that, the
fact that he said it, you know, the fact that the story
was that he stopped after three, that's because they only asked after
three. Maybe if they asked after two, he would have stopped after
two. It says no. אי כן מאי אסיתיה דרבי חייא בר אבא?
Ee kein mai asuysei de-Rabbi Chiya bar Abba? No,
then why would רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba bother
to have told the story? If it was, well, but he obviously,
he obviously knew enough of the circumstances. It's trying to tell you
it might not be communicated in the words, but obviously the circumstances
must have been such that, that he said don't worry after two
and he only says it's a problem after three, because otherwise there's
nothing to teach about this story. So the גמרא Gemara says that's
not true, there is something to teach about this story. What's there
to teach? What all of you were noticing. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ודילמא הא קא משמע לן דאחיות מחזקות. ve-dilma ha ka mashma
lan de-achayos machazkos. Maybe it's telling you that you can learn out
from one sister to another sister, that something that happened with one
sister is relevant in terms of the kids of the other sister
when it comes to this issue of ברית מילה Bris Milah and
there's a good reason. Because why would baby boys be dying as
a result of ברית
מילה? Bris Milah? Hemophilia, which passes through the the women, right, passes
on to the the males, right? Everybody know hemophilia? No, that classic
case you learned in high school in in genetics about the which
family was it? The Russian family, right, the Russian czar family. Anyway,
so that's exactly it. The sisters, right, if there's a hemophilia gene,
it's passing through the sisters and you know and it's being expressed
in the baby boys, so that's אחיות מחזקות achayos machazkos and you
can learn it out from, and therefore if you see it by
one sister's baby, you have to be concerned with the other sister
as well. Okay and that's a pretty big חידוש. chiddush.
They actually say that?
Yeah, okay, yeah. So that it's almost, it's almost universally assumed that
all these גמרות Gemaras are talking about hemophilia and it works perfectly
because of that theory about the, you know, around the around the
sisters and so on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So we don't have a reconciliation, so we don't know, we can't
prove which is רבי Rabbi and which is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, but nevertheless we're going to assume that רבי
Rabbi is two and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
is three. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר
רבא השתא דאמרת אחיות מחזקות, Amar Rava, hashta de-amart achayos machazkos, now
that you say you can like sort of learn from one sister
to the other, you know, apply the apply the evidence, so לא
ישא אדם אשה לא ממשפחת נכפין ולא ממשפחת מצורעין. lo yissa adam
isha lo mi-mishpachas nichpin ve-lo mishpachas metzora'in.
A person shouldn't marry a woman from a family that has epilepsy
and or a family with leprosy.
והוא דאתחזק תלתא זימני. Ve-hu de-itchazek tlata zimni. And that's if it
happened three times. But again, even if it didn't happen with this
woman, if it happened with her sisters or with other people in
the family, you can infer things from other family members and you
have to take that into account. And of course this leads, as
we know, to a whole sad phenomenon that exists now particularly in
the חרדי Chareidi world, you know, which is like oh you know
if any one of the, oh there was ever any problem, I
heard they had an uncle that had some issue with blah blah
blah and then people get completely stigmatized, you know, about I think
it's epilepsy.
Yeah, epilepsy.
I hear how tough it is. He has to make sure that
you do not, she does not have two patients with epilepsy in
the hospital at the same time from the same Chassidic group. Because?
Because they don't, they don't want anyone to know. They come to
Montefiore rather than a hospital in Brooklyn so that nobody else in
their community will know.
But then they don't want to have anybody of their community in
the hospital at the same time, not just somebody else with epilepsy.
Well, it's a huge hospital. Right.
But you know, that's why they also have this what is it
דור ישרים Dor Yeshorim where you can do genetic testing, but the
way the genetic testing works is you never get a report on
your own testing, all you get told is whether you're a match,
whether you're a problem with the person you're interested in, yeah, because
it's so concerned about you know that a stigma in the family
that there was some problem somewhere in that family. So the גמרא
Gemara has it but in a lighter way, I mean it has
a very serious condition and only if it happened three times you
know does the גמרא Gemara sort of say. But then nevertheless the
conclusion is don't marry a woman once you know that's the problem
of that family.
So, look these issues that we deal with even up until today.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. והוא, Ve-hu, okay, מאי
הוה עלה? mai hava alah? So what was the conclusion about who
held what between רבי Rabbi and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel? So כי אתא רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר עובדא הוה
קמי דרבי יוחנן בכנישתא דמעון, ki asa Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar
uvda hava kammai de-Rabbi Yochanan be-kneishta de-Ma'on, a story happened with רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in the בית כנסת Beis Knesset of, in the
synagogue of Ma'on. ביומא דכיפורי שחל להיות בשבת, Be-yoma di-kippura she-chal lihyos
be-Shabbos, just to raise the stakes, it was Yom Kippur and Shabbos,
and they were doing a ברית מילה, Bris Milah, and it was
a question whether the kid was going to survive or not. ומלה
ראשונה ומת, u-malla lishona u-mes, ושנייה ומת, shniya u-mes,
you have all these kids dying in the שול shul during ברית
מילה Bris Milah on Shabbos. ושלישית, ve-shlishis, the third kid, presumably all
the same day. All the same day, I don't know if it's
triplets, three sisters all gave birth on the same day, I don't
know what it was. שלישית בא לפניו, shlishis ba lefanav, the third
case, maybe those two happened on an earlier day, and the third
case was on שבת יום כיפור. Shabbos Yom Kippur. I don't know.
אמר לה amar lah and he says so, it came to רב
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and he said to her, לכי ומולי lechi u'moli
go and do a ברית מילה. bris milah. אמר ליה אביי, amar
lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said to him, חזי דקשרית איסורא וסכנתא.
chazi de'kashris issura ve'sakanta. So אביי Abaye said to רב יצחק בר
יוסף Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef
who reported this in the name of רב יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, notice
on your testimony you are basically permitting איסור issur and סכנה. sakana.
איסור issur is you're going to the... we're going to do a
ברית מילה bris milah on, you know, on שבת יום כיפור Shabbos
Yom Kippur whatever, and not say... because if you're not allowed to
do a ברית מילה bris milah because סכנת נפשות sakanas nefashos then
it's a חילול שבת. chilul Shabbos. And number two, you're potentially exposing
this kid to סכנת נפשות. sakanas nefashos. So it's a free... it's
not a trivial פסק psak by any... by any result, by you
know, by any measure. Okay, and that's if you rule like, what
do you call it? That's if you rule like רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. סמך עליה אביי, samach alei Abaye, so
then אביי Abaye
although he sort of pointed out how you know how weighty that
implications were, he relied on it. ואזל ונסבה, v'azal v'nasbah, he went
and he married לחומא le'Choma this woman by the name of חומא,
Choma, ברתיה דאיסי בריה דרב יצחק, bartia de'Issi brei de'Rav Yitzchak, the
daughter of איסי Issi the son of רב יצחק, Rav Yitzchak, בריה
דרב יהודה. brei d'Rav Yehuda. Now what was the story about חומא?
Choma? דנסבה רחבא דפומבדיתא, de'nasbah Rechava d'Pumbedisa, רחבא דפומבדיתא Rechava d'Pumbedisa had
already married this woman, ושכיב, ve'shachiv, and he had died. רב יצחק
בריה דרבה בר בר חנה Rav Yitzchak brei de'Rabbah bar bar Chana
had married this woman, ושכיב, ve'shachiv, and he had died. So now
we are getting, we had two babies dying, we have a woman
not being able to have kids with two different husbands, and does
that you know... and now we're getting two husbands of a woman
married to two husbands who both died. Does that prove that... that
somehow there's something about being married to this woman that causes their
husbands to die? So and nevertheless he said no, it's only two
times, we're פוסק paskening three times until three times it's not a
problem. ונסבה, v'nasvah, he married her, ושכיב, ve'shachiv, and he died.
אמר רבא, amar Rava, אמר רבא, amar Rava, ומי איכא דעביד עובדא
בנפשיה כי האי? u'mi ika de'avid uvda be'nafshei ki hai? Who... where
would you ever find somebody to experiment on themselves other than like
אביי Abaye like a... you know he felt very confident, right? You
don't use yourself to do the experiment. I don't know, other people
either, but anyway. Alright, so anyway all this now is we're pointing
to the fact that we have to start פוסק paskening like רבי
Rebbi and start worrying especially when people's lives are potentially at stake,
start worrying after two times. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
אימור דאמר אבין דסמכינן יצחק סומכא לאו בר סמכא. eimar de'amar Avin
de'samchinan Yitzchak Sumcha lav bar samcha. Now why did he rely on
this teaching in the name of רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan from יצחק
בר יוסף? Yitzchak bar Yosef? אביי Abaye himself said that אבין Avin
you can rely on when he reports things in the name of
רב יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. יצחק Yitzchak the red, for whatever reason that
was his name, is somebody that you can't rely on. אבין ישנו
בחזרה Avin yeshno be'chazarah because אבין Avin either re... you know reviews
his you know what he has learned, or the way רש"י Rashi
says it is he always goes back and double checks with רב
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to see if רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan possibly reversed
himself. יצחק סומכא אינו בחזרה. Yitzchak Sumcha eino be'chazarah. יצחק סומכא Yitzchak
Sumcha doesn't review his learning or doesn't double check with רב יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. So you can't usually rely on what רב יצחק Rav
Yitzchak says in the name of רב יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Why did
he rely on it? ועוד ve'od
דפליגי בעניין מילה. de'paligi b'inyan milah. Even if רבי Rebbi and רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel דפליגי, de'paligi, when do רבי
Rebbi and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel debate? בעניין
מילה be'inyan milah by ברית מילה. bris milah. בנישואין מי פליגי? be'nisuin
mi paligi? Since when do they debate by getting married? Presumably meaning
that everybody would be more concerned about marrying this woman, not exactly
clear, if anything you would think it's more reason to be concerned
about the babies, you know, it's more obvious the cause and effect
relationship there than by the marriage. Okay, well that too. אין, in,
yes, they also do debate by marriage. דתניא, de'sanya, it was shown
in a ברייתא, baraisa, נישאת לראשון ומת לשני ומת לשלישי לא תינשא
דברי רבי. nisas le'rishon umes le'sheni umes le'shlishi lo sinasei divrei Rebbi.
So marriage, first one and second one dies, don't get married, third
man shouldn't marry her. That's what רבי Rebbi says. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר לשלישי תינשא לרביעי לא תינשא. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer
le'shlishi sinasei le'revi'i lo sinasei. No, third guy can marry her, it's
only the fourth guy you can't. בשלמא bishlama now, we want to
understand what is the causal relationship. So we don't have an answer
why אביי Abaye relied on this פסק, psak, maybe he really wanted
to marry חומא, Choma, so he decided to lie on the פסק,
psak, but anywa... חומא Choma I mean, excuse me. But nevertheless, all
of the evidence is pointed, right, to the idea, logic would be
pointed like start worrying after two times, and that certainly is what
happened here, you know the case of אביי Abaye brings out.
Now let's understand, these names are Wall and Plaza?
Yeah, basically. Now let's take a look. Now let's understand what is
אביי... Abaye... what is the issues about how these things could be
happening. So you know what is the assumption if it happens two,
three times, what's sort of the cause of all of this? So
בשלמא גבי מילה איכא משפחה דרפי דמא ואיכא משפחה דקמיט דמא. bishlama
gabi milah ika mishpacha de'rafi dama ve'ika mishpacha de'kamit dama. By מילה
milah I understand, there's some families... I understand what the cause of
relationship is. There are some families that have loose blood and some
have like a more viscous blood, you know, so basically a way
of saying it's a blood bleeding problem that's runs in the family.
אלא נישואין מאי טעמא? ela nisuin mai ta'ama? What's the reason by
marriage that just because two husbands died on her we have to
assume that every husband is going to die? So אמר ליה רב
מרדכי לרב אשי, הכי אמר ביבי מהגרוניא משמיה דרב הונא: מעין גורם.
Amar lei Rav Mordechai le-Rav Ashi, hachi amar Bibi mi-Agronya mi-shmeih de-Rav
Huna: Mayan gorem. Somehow the מעין, mayan, which means the wellspring, somehow
the sex with her is somehow bringing this about. Now it’s not
exactly saying what, I don’t know, are we to say that she
has a venereal disease? I don’t know what it’s assuming. But somehow
it's a result of having sex with her, we're assuming maybe creates
some illness. ורב אשי אמר מזל גורם. Ve-Rav Ashi amar mazal gorem.
No, it’s just pure the מזל mazal of being married to her.
So it’s nothing to do with any more of a, I don’t
know, a medical type of explanation, it's just somehow she's bad luck.
So מאי בינייהו, Mai beinaihu, what would be a difference between these
reasons? איכא בינייהו דארס ומת, Ika beinaihu de-airas u-meis, that a husband
died before נישואין, nisuin, after אירוסין. eirusin. So it couldn't be based
on having, resulting from sexual activity, it must have been, but it
would have worked, but if the מזל mazal is an issue, that
would be an issue there too. אי נמי, Ei nami, and here's
a more clear example I think, דנפל מדיקלא ומת. de-nafal mi-dikla u-meis.
He fell out of a tree and he died. Okay, you know,
it reminds me of this short story, right? About that there's this
party and they're eating these wild mushrooms and they say, "Like how
could you, you know, how do you know the problem? No, we
fed it to our dog, everything's okay." And then the maid comes
in and says, "Oh my god, Fido has just died," and everybody
like runs to the hospital, the emergency room, gets a stomach, and
turns out that like he was hit by a car.
So anyway, if the guy falls out of the tree and dies,
it has nothing to do with the
relationship, with having had sex with his wife. But if it's a
מזל mazal issue, it's bad luck to be married to this woman,
so it doesn't matter how he dies. Okay, יפה. Yafeh.
Right.
That's a good point, although there it's much more clear that it
has to do with their actions, but which does prove that it
could happen not relating to, right, it's good evidence that sometimes, you
know, things happen twice in a row and it still doesn't prove
anything. Right. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so אמר ליה רב
יוסף לאביי ולרבא. Amar lei Rav Yosef le-Abaye ve-le-Rava. So we still
don't know what the הלכה halacha is. Obviously, I think all of
us would be inclined to say that the, you know, to play
it safe after two times, especially by the case of the infants.
Other cases, like the fertility issue and so on, I mean, we
feel like we'll go to a doctor, but they didn't have that
as an option, you know. So let's take a look.
I'm sorry, when they say הלכה, halacha, they're saying it for all
these cases?
We didn't פסקן pasken yet. What are you talking about? לרבא, בעא
מיניה מרב יוסף. Le-Rava, ba'ei mineih me-Rav Yosef. I asked of רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, הלכה כרבי? Halacha ke-Rebbi? I'm sorry, בעא מיניה, ba'ei
mineih, I asked of רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, הלכה כרבי, Halacha ke-Rebbi,
do we rule like רבי? Rebbi? ואמר לי אין. Ve-amar li in.
He said, "Yes." Then I said to him, הלכה כרבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, Halacha ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, do we rule like רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל? Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? ואמר לי אין. Ve-amar li in.
He says, "Yes." So
אחיוכי אחיך בי, Achyuchei achyuch bi, I thought he was making fun
of me. אמר לי, Amar li, he said to me, "לא, Lo,
no, סתמי היא." Stamei hi. He's telling, it's a סתם משנה. stam
Mishnah. ופשיט לכו, U-pashit lechu, I mean no, I, I'm sorry, he's
reporting to רבא, Rava, so I think that רב יוסף Rav Yosef
is making fun of me. And רבא Rava says, "No, he's just
telling you that we פסקן pasken different ways in different
cases." Okay. ופשיט לכו, U-pashit lechu, and they're סתם משנה. stam Mishnah.
So נישואין ומלקיות כרבי, Nisuin u-malkiyos ke-Rebbi, by being married and lashes
we rule like רבי, Rebbi, two times. ווסתות ושור המועד כרבן שמעון
בן גמליאל, Vestos ve-shor ha-muad ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, by ווסתות vestos
and שור המועד shor ha-muad we go like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. What does this mean? נישואין הא דאמרן, Nisuin
ha de-amran, נישואין nisuin we said, a guy's married twice, two guys
married to the same woman died, third person shouldn't marry her. מלקיות
דתנן, Malkiyos de-tenan, מי שלקה ושנה, mi she-lakah ve-shanah, somebody got מלקות
malkos and did it twice, you know, twice did the same sin
and got מלקות malkos twice. So clearly this is a repeat offender,
so what's בית דין Beis Din going to do to this guy?
Obviously the מלקות malkos isn't stopping him. So בית דין כונסין אותו
לכיפה ומאכילין אותו שעורין עד שתבקע כריסו ויומת. Beis Din konasin oso
la-kippah u-ma'achilin oso seorin ad she-tibaka kreiso ve-yumas. You put him into
this jail, into this כיפה, kippah, and you feed him grain until
his stomach bursts. Now where, well right, so we're inclined to read
it and the גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין Sanhedrin that it literally means
you feed him some mixture of grain and water that expands and
causes the stomach to burst. התוספות Ha-Tosafos points out that the פשט
pshat of this is probably just means, you know, you feed him
as much grain as you want, like you know, it's a metaphor,
it doesn't, you know, you feed him as much grain to stuff
his, you know, you know, don't give him fancy stuff, just give
him barley, but give him barley so much barley until his stomach,
you know, gets, you know, bursts as a result, but not literally,
just as much as you want. Anyway, but the point is, you
do something with him even if he's just a repeat offender twice.
You don't wait until he's a repeat offender three times before taking
drastic action. This action is taken after twice.
What about the three?
ווסתות Vestos we talk about in a minute. ווסתות דתנן, Vestos de-tenan,
how about a ווסת, veses, which is a woman's period? When we
assume that she's expecting her period, because we talk in the Mishnah,
אין אשה קובעת לה ווסת, ein ishah kova'as lah veses, a woman
doesn't establish a regular menstrual period עד שתקבענה שלש פעמים. ad she-tikba'enah
shalosh pe'amim. ואינה מטהרת מן הווסת עד שתעקרנה שלש פעמים. Ve-einah mitahares
min ha-veses ad she-ta'akrenah shalosh pe'amim. Once she has a regular period,
we don't assume that it's changed until it's gone three months being
different and that has all these implications about when she has to
be concerned that she will bleed or if the if the period
passes even if she didn't do a check, she has to assume
that she did bleed and she became a נדה niddah and so
on. We assume it came during the regular period. That we need
three times. ושור המועד דתנן, Ve-shor ha-muad de-tenan, and the and the
habitual ox that pays full and not half damage. is because the
משנה mishna says אין השור נעשה מועד עד שיעידו בו שלוש פעמים,
ein hashor nase muad ad sheyeidu bo shalosh p'amim, it's only after
it's done it three times. So the question is on the fourth
time he's a מועד. muad. So the question is, okay, but how
can you split your vote? What's the story? Is it two times,
is it three times? And the best explanation said by a number
of אחרונים, achronim, I think the פני יהושע pnei yehoshua says it,
and others, is what I told you before. That two times already
is enough that we don't say it's a freak occurrence and we
say we have to start worrying about this. But it doesn't mean
we say it's definitely going to happen. The idea, for example, about
a woman having her period or the שור המועד, shor hamuad, that
doesn't just tell you oh, we have to be concerned that she
might bleed on this day. It says no, we assume that she
bled when she's expecting her period. Or by the ox, we assume
that he now is—his identity is not just somebody be a little
careful, he's done it once or twice, no. His identity—the identity is
it's an—it's a habitual gorer, right? So three times establishes that it
is regular, it is habitual, we know for sure. Two times establishes
like we gotta start being concerned about it. It's sort of like
what the—what, you know, the חפץ חיים's Chofetz Chaim discussion about לשון
הרע. lashon hara. You don't have to believe it to be חושש
choshesh for it, okay? So three times you believe it—I mean, not
by לשון הרע—three lashon hara times we say it's definitely a pattern,
it's happening, etc. Two times you're חושש. choshesh. And that's why, to
put a guy, let's assume you're not executing him. I mean, if
you're executing him, it's a little worse. But let's assume to put
a guy in jail because he's habitual, you know, you're concerned that
he's a troublemaker or so on, it's a way of—sort of—it's a
way of dealing with it even if now maybe that's a little
bit harder to understand. But certainly the idea of the ברית מילה,
bris milah, right? Don't do a ברית מילה bris milah after twice.
I mean, we would say even after once, you know, I don't
know what
we—but—but certainly after twice where you—you get a doctor involved. Okay. And
similarly therefore presumably that gets back to our משנה. mishna. Our משנה
mishna about a woman after she's two—when two periods of ten years
not having kids, you have to assume that she's infertile. And the
third guy, if she hasn't had kids, shouldn't marry her. You have
to assume that this woman is infertile, meaning or even if not
definitely, right, maybe—look, here's the story. When she gets divorced—and this is
what the גמרא's Gemara going to get to, this actually exactly proves
this, this will prepare us for tomorrow—when she gets divorced from the
second husband, the second husband has to still give her a כתובה.
k'suva. So it actually proves the case exactly. She went two periods
of ten years, second husband gives her a כתובה, k'suva, which means
we can't prove that she's infertile, right? We have to still say
maybe it's his problem, not her problem. But because of like רבי,
Rebbe, the third guy shouldn't marry her. So which is it? Is
she infertile or not infertile? So the answer is we don't know,
okay? There's enough reason to suspect that she is that the third
guy, if he still hasn't done פרו ורבו, pru u'rvu, isn't allowed
to marry her because it's in this zone after two. But because
it's not yet evident that she is, the second guy still has
to give her a כתובה. k'suva. So that's exactly the space between
רבי Rebbe and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, between
the idea of enough to be concerned about but not enough to
establish as a fact. And presumably the same would be about the
woman whose two husbands die on her, but of course there you
do wonder whether like for us the causal aspects there are a
lot weaker, so one wonders, you know, that—that's a little bit more
like questionable about how to apply that nowadays. Okay, to be continued
tomorrow.
Why you think מזל's mazal less reliable? Yeah, exactly.
So what do we say?